Jack: So, let’s look at the
principles of compiled code and
interpreted code in more detail.
With compiled code the program is
written in the source language.
The code is then run through a
separate program called a compiler.
The compiler decomposes the original
code, parses it into components
and generates an executable file.
This executable file is called a “binary”.
The binary can then be executed
separately to run the program.
Leah: Since a binary must be generated
to run the program with compiled code,
this can make testing take longer, as
this must be done every time a change
is made which requires a new test.
However, since the conversion to machine
code is done during the process of
generating an executable file, this means
that compiled codes can run faster as
this aspect of the work is already done.
Jack: Before writing a binary,
the compiler will run a check for
syntax on the original source code.
If there are errors, it
will flag a message and it
will not be able to compile.
If there are no syntax errors, it
continues compiling the program
to generate a binary file.
Compilers must convert source
code to a binary, which runs on
the specific operating system
that they are being compiled for.
Leah: Compiled programs are therefore not
cross-platform, meaning that they cannot
be run directly from the source code
on incompatible operating systems/CPUs.
However, it is possible to generate
binaries from the source code
which run on different systems
using the appropriate compiler.
Examples of compiled languages
are C, C++, Objective-C
Jack: With Interpreted code the program
is written in the source language.
When the program is executed, the
original source code is run line by
line through a separate program called
an interpreter in real time code.
As
Leah: it runs, the interpreter
“translates” the source code into actions
which are then executable line by line.
Interpreted code can be easy
to debug, as the code can be
run whilst it is being written.
This is often done using a
program called an Integrated
Development Environment [IDE].
This is a program used for development
where the code can be edited, but also has
a built-in interpreter for the language.
The code can therefore be run within
the IDE [for example Spyder for Python,
and Microsoft Visual Studio, which
has plug-ins for different languages].
Jack: When the code is run, the
interpreter runs the program line by
line, checking for syntax errors, then
performing the operations directly.
If an error is encountered on any line,
the operation of the program will halt
in the state that it is in when the
error occurs, unless instructions on how
to deal with the error are written in.
Leah: Interpreted code can essentially
be run on any operating system
or CPU, providing that there is
an interpreter for that system.
This means that the programs themselves
can be much more “portable”, but
that they may take longer to run
that compiled programs as they
are translated as they are run.
Examples of Interpreted
languages are PHP, JavaScript.
Jack: In order to get the
compatibility of interpretation
and the speed of normal compilation
[ahead-of-time], another method of
interpretation has been developed.
This is called just-in-time [JIT]
compilation and it is where some
compilation occurs ahead of time through
an intermediate called byte code.
Leah: The byte code converts as
much of the program into machine
code as is possible whilst still
being portable across platforms.
The remaining parts are then
interpreted on a machine/operating
system-specific interpreter.
Examples of this Hybrid are
Java, C#, VB.NET, Python.